As if the 2020s couldn't get any
crazier, something that most of the
world probably assumed had been left
behind in the early 2010s is suddenly
beginning to happen again off the coast
of Somalia. The Somali pirates have
returned back onto the global stage once
again. Throughout just a few months in
2026, armed pirate groups operating from
the coast of Somalia were able to
successfully capture four commercial
merchant ships, putting the pace of
Somali piracy related hijackings on
course to be the highest this year in
more than a decade since 2012. As of the
end of July, all four of these hijacked
merchant ships still remain anchored
closely together just off of the
northern coast of Somalia with their 67
crew members all still being held
hostage on board and with the pirates
still demanding millions of dollars in
ransom cash for their safe [music]
release. The first of these vessels, a
Palo flagged oil tanker called the Honor
25, was hijacked on the 21st of April by
a group of Somali pirates approximately
30 nautical miles off the coast of
Somalia. The ship had been traveling
towards the Somali capital of Mogadishu
with [music] 18 12,000 barrels refined
oil on board to try and relieve an acute
fuel shortage that had developed there.
Then just 5 days later on the 26th of
April, another different group of Somali
pirates managed to hijack a St. Kits and
NeAs flag cargo ship called the Sward
just off of the northern coast of
Somalia as it was traveling towards
Kenya with a full cargo of fertilizer.
And then less than a week after that
one, on the 2nd of May, more Somali
pirates managed to pull off a very
brazen hijacking of the Togo flagged oil
tanker Eureka while she was anchored
just outside of the port of Kana in
southern Yemen on the complete other
side of the Gulf of Aiden away from
Somalia. Those three successful maritime
hijackings by Somali pirates in only a
matter of weeks rattled the global
maritime industry. But for the next
couple of months, [music] a relative
quiet set in that led some analysts to
assume that they might have been
isolated incidents. But then on the 17th
of July, the pirates suddenly struck
again when they seized another oil
tanker, the Tanzania flagged Asana, as
it was sailing approximately 65 nautical
miles southwest of Macala, Yemen,
through the Gulf of Aiden. In all four
of these hijackings, none of the ships
involved had any armed security on
board, which made them easier targets.
while all four of them were subsequently
sailed by the pirates back towards the
northern Somalia coastline where they
have all remained anchored close
together with their crews all held
captive while ransom negotiations
continue. And even more concerningly,
the pirates have begun demonstrating
that they still remember all of the same
tricks that had made them so successful
the last time Somali piracy exploded
onto the world stage around 15 years
ago. After they captured the large 330
foot long sward cargo ship in April,
they began using it as a pirate mother
ship, sailing it up and down the coast
of Somalia and launching smaller
speedboats from it to go out and capture
other vessels nearby. In July, two
smaller Iranian fishing boats were also
seized by these pirate speedboats that
were operating from the sward in a
highly coordinated attack. And at one
point at least six hijacked vessels were
simultaneously being held off of the
Somali coast. When one of the suspected
pirate leaders who was involved in the
swar hijacking was arrested by local
Somali authorities and brought to
[music] a police station, armed militia
men actually attacked that police
station the following day in an attempt
to free him, which triggered a gunfight
that killed one policeman and injured
another. [music] And all of this is
beginning to look disturbingly familiar
because only about 15 years ago, [music]
Somali piracy was regarded as the single
greatest scourge to the international
shipping industry anywhere on the
planet. Between 2005 and 2012, Somali
pirates exploded onto the global
consciousness. They launched more than a
thousand attacks against foreign ships
during this period, successfully
hijacked 218 of them, and took more than
3,700 foreign sailors as hostages. At
the absolute peak of the Somali piracy
crisis in 2011, there were more than 230
pirate attacks in just that single year.
Upwards of 700 sailors were being held
hostage simultaneously, while the total
cost imposed upon the global economy by
piracy around Somalia reached somewhere
around $7 billion a year. A hidden tax
on global commerce that was raising the
price of goods all around the world. Big
super successful Hollywood blockbuster
movies like Captain Phillips were coming
out at the time about the crisis.
[music] While Somali piracy became so
deeply ingrained in the cultural psyche
of the United States that to many
Americans even today, the first thing
that comes to their mind when they hear
Somalia is unfortunately pirate. But
then almost as suddenly as Somali piracy
had appeared, it seemed to disappear.
There were 237 reported Somali piracy
attacks in 2011. But by the time 2012
rolled around, that number had declined
to only 75, which crashed even further
to only 15 across all of 2013 and then
only 11 in 2014. [music] There were zero
successful merchant ship hijackings at
all between 2013 and 2016. [music]
Just one successful hijacking in 2017
and then none whatsoever at all between
2018 and 2022.
For nearly a decade between 2013 and
2022, that sole successful hijacking in
2017 was the only one that Somali
pirates managed to pull off, which most
analysts wrote off as a one-off isolated
incident. By the start of 2023, the
scourge of Somali piracy appeared to
have been so thoroughly defeated that
the International Maritime Bureau
formally removed the Western Indian
Ocean's designation as a high-risk area
for piracy. But then only months after
they did so in December of 2023 came the
hijacking of the MV ruined by Somali
pirates. The first successful hijacking
of a merchant ship by them in more than
6 years. [music]
Followed by another successful hijacking
in 2024, another round of relative calm
in 2025. And now four more successful
hijackings just [music] through the end
of July in 2026.
a rate of piracy that is still well
below the levels they were at back in
2011, but which still nonetheless shows
a clear trend. For the first time since
the peak of the Somali piracy crisis
back in 2011, the rate of Somali piracy
is increasing yet again. So, how did a
bunch of ragtag pirates operating from
one of the most impoverished and least
developed countries on the planet
managed to become one of the most
significant threats to global shipping
in the first place? How did an
unprecedented international coalition of
countries as geopolitically diverse as
the US, EU, Russia, China, and India
manage to nearly eliminate them? And
perhaps most importantly now, why are
the Somali pirates suddenly starting to
come back again? To understand all of
this, we need to go back about 35 years
ago, back to the complete collapse of
Somalia itself and the start of
Somalia's status as the world's most
infamous [music] failed state. After
years of brutal internal civil war in
January of 1991, the two decadel long
communist dictatorship of Sad Bareet
finally collapsed in Somalia. And with
it went almost the entire Somali state
as well. Government institutions
throughout most of the country simply
[music] ceased functioning almost
overnight. The Somali military
disintegrated and the country shattered
apart between various rival clans,
warlords, militias, and eventually
Islamist insurgencies. And this societal
collapse created a particularly unusual
problem for Somalia because of the
country's geography. Somalia possesses
more than 3,300 km of coastline
stretching along the Gulf of Aiden in
the Indian Ocean. The longest coastline
of any country in mainland Africa. And
when the government collapsed in early
1991, the entire Somali Navy and Coast
Guard effectively disappeared right
along with it. one of the longest and
most strategically important coastlines
anywhere in the world was suddenly left
with virtually nobody around to actually
police it. [music] This coastline also
happens to sit immediately beside one of
the busiest maritime highways on the
planet. Ships traveling between Europe
and Asia through the Suez Canal have to
pass through the narrow Babelman dev
straight between the Gulf of Aiden and
the Red [music] Sea immediately to the
north of Somalia. Roughly 10 to 15% of
all the world's seaborn [music] trade
usually passes through this general area
as a result. Meaning that thousands of
enormous cargo ships, container ships,
bulk carriers, and oil tankers were
constantly [music] sailing past a
country that by the 1990s effectively
possessed no government, no navy, no
coast guard, no functioning court
system, nor any police force capable of
stopping anybody from attacking them.
But before pirates from Somalia began
seriously attacking and raiding these
merchant ships, [music] the initial
targets they chose were usually smaller
foreign fishing vessels. The waters
offshore of Somalia contain extremely
valuable and productive stocks of tuna
and other fish. And [snorts] once there
was no longer any Somali government
capable of enforcing the country's
maritime borders, foreign fishing
vessels from all across the Middle East,
Asia, and elsewhere began increasingly
taking advantage of the situation by
moving in to take whatever they could
without any oversight. Estimates for
precisely how much illegal fishing took
place in Somali waters throughout the
1990s and 2000s vary significantly, and
some of the larger claims are difficult
to independently verify. But there is
still very little doubt that rampant
illegal and unregulated foreign fishing
became a major grievance among Somalia's
coastal communities during this era
where many local Somali fishermen came
to believe that enormous industrial
trwers from the other side of the world
were stealing their fish, out competing
them, ripping up the ocean floor,
destroying their livelihoods, and
leaving them behind with increasingly
little left to catch themselves. For a
country with little other legitimate
economic opportunities beyond fishing,
this was all completely catastrophic.
And at roughly [music] the same time,
allegations also began swirling
throughout Somalia that foreign
companies and criminal organizations
were taking advantage of the absence of
a government by illegally dumping
hazardous waste in Somalia's waters,
too. Claims have ranged from ordinary
industrial and medical waste all the way
up to radioactive material. And the
evidence supporting the full scale of
these allegations remains mixed and
disputed. But then in 2004, a massive
earthquake on the other side of the
Indian Ocean triggered the deadliest
tsunami in human history that swept
across the entire region. The coastline
of Somalia was not spared from the
tsunami's fury and nearly 300 people in
Somalia were killed and 50,000 more were
displaced after it impacted. But the
tsunami also caused containers full of
hazardous materials to begin washing
ashore in Somalia, too, lending some
credibility to at least some of the
allegations of illegal offshore dumping
by foreigners in the 1990s.
Regardless of precisely how extensive
the dumping actually was, the important
point for understanding what came next
is that many Somali genuinely believed
that foreign countries were taking
advantage of them by simultaneously
stealing most of the fish out of their
waters and then dumping poisonous waste
back into them in return. And so during
the 1990s and the early 2000s, groups of
armed Somali fishermen began taking
matters into their own [music] hands.
Some of these groups that began forming
started referring to themselves as
volunteer coast guards that began
approaching foreign fishing vessels in
Somalia's waters, boarding them, and
demanding payments for supposed fishing
licenses, fines, or compensation for
operating illegally inside of Somali
waters. In some cases, the fishermen
involved may have genuinely viewed
themselves as vigilantes defending their
country's resources in the absence of
any actual government capable of doing
it instead. In other cases though, the
supposed fines they were enforcing were
obviously little more than thinly veiled
armed extortion. Throughout the 1990s
and the early 2000s, this was basically
how Somali piracy functioned, and it was
small scale enough to effectively just
blend into the background noise of
global affairs. Piracy around Somalia
was not yet high enough to set it apart
from other global piracy hotspots like
the Gulf of Guinea or the Straight of
Mala. But eventually the distinction
between Somali vigilante and Somali
pirate stopped mattering entirely
because the fishermen who were getting
themselves involved in a piracy began
realizing something extremely important.
There was dramatically more money to be
made from capturing one of those
enormous [music]
and usually undefended commercial ships
sailing past Somalia through the Gulf of
Aiden than there was ever going to be
from fishing or from extorting smaller
foreign fishing vessels.
Just one captured merchant ship could
potentially earn more money through a
ransom payment than an entire Somali
fishing [music] village could make
across multiple years.
And once that realization became
widespread during the early 2000s,
Somali piracy rapidly began evolving
away from anything that could plausibly
be described as vigilante coastg guard
activity and into [music] an
increasingly sophisticated organized
criminal industry instead. And it really
did start becoming an industry. By the
mid to late 2000s, a successful Somali
pirate expedition could involve dozens
or even hundreds of people on land and
at sea, fulfilling highly specialized
roles. Investors would provide the money
up front to purchase boats, engines,
weapons, fuel, food, GPS systems, and
satellite phones. Recruiters would go
out and find young men willing to
actually go out to sea and conduct the
attacks. Experienced operational leaders
would organize the expeditions and
decide where to go and search for
targets. Armed gunmen would board and
seize the ships, while other men would
subsequently guard the captured sailors
on land for months at a time.
Translators and negotiators who could
speak English or other languages would
communicate with the ship owners,
insurance companies, governments, and
families to negotiate the ransom
payment, while clan elders and local
political elites would provide
protection on shore. And once the ransom
money eventually arrived, still more
people were needed to move it around,
distribute everybody's shares, pay
bribes, and launder the proceeds. In
effect, many pirate expeditions began
functioning almost like extremely
violent startup companies in Silicon
Valley. Somebody with money could invest
in a pirate expedition by paying for a
portion of the equipment and operating
costs. And if that expedition
successfully captured a ship and
collected a ransom, that investor would
receive an agreed upon percentage of the
profits in return. The actual pirates
who went out to sea were essentially the
high-risk employees who might return
home with tens of thousands of dollars
if everything worked out, but might also
return back with nothing, get arrested
by a foreign navy, or simply die out at
sea if it didn't work out. The potential
rewards, however, were almost
unimaginably large by Somali standards.
An individual pirate involved in a
successful operation from start to
finish might end up walking away with
somewhere between $10,000 and $75,000
at the end of it. In a country where the
average annual income was only around
$700.
In other words, a young Somali man
turned pirate could potentially earn an
entire lifetimes worth of ordinary
income through just a single successful
hijacking. No wonder then that so many
of them started doing it. And after
successfully collecting a ransom once,
the pirates could reinvest that money
into buying heavier weapons, bigger
[music] ships, more supplies, and more
gunmen to launch even more ambitious
raids for even bigger ransoms before
doing it all over again in a violent
cycle that continued snowballing
throughout the 2000s. Warlords in
Somalia eventually began noticing the
economic opportunity that was available
in piracy and began putting up their own
resources into funding operations to get
a return. And the enormous amounts of
money that began flowing into piracy
inevitably transformed some of the small
coastal communities where the pirates
were operating from. Coastal towns in
Somalia like Ae, Oio, and Hared here
transformed into the most famous pirate
strongholds where captured vessels could
be anchored offshore for months at a
time. While negotiations continued,
pirate money flowed through the local
economies and a restaurants, hotels,
vehicles, housing, supplies, and
virtually everything else that was
required to keep dozens of captured
ships and hundreds of hostages all
functioning. The pirate groups couldn't
operate in isolation from these
communities. They needed huge amounts of
support on land, which meant that ransom
money had to be spread around enough to
make continued piracy locally
worthwhile. But before any of that money
could actually be made, the pirates
still had to somehow capture one of
those huge merchant ships at sea in the
first place. And by the late 2000s, they
had gotten disturbingly good at it. A
typical attack often began aboard a
larger, previously captured fishing
vessel or traditional DAO that the
pirates used as a mother ship. the small
speedboats that the pirates actually
used for their attacks at extremely
limited ranges by themselves. But a
larger mother ship could carry the
pirates their fuel, food, weapons, and
several smaller skiffs hundreds of
kilometers deep out into the [music]
Indian Ocean. Once the mother ship
located a vulnerable merchant vessel,
two or three skiffs carrying around six
to 10 armed pirates each could be
launched into the water and accelerated
towards the target ship at a much faster
speed than it was capable of escaping
away at. As the skiffs closed the
distance, the pirates would begin firing
assault rifles and sometimes even RPGs
towards the ship, but almost always more
for intimidation rather than actually
trying to sink or disable the ship. If
they destroyed the ship, after all, they
wouldn't be able to collect their
ransom. Once they got alongside, the
pirates would throw up grappling hooks
or raise lightweight ladders against the
hole and climb themselves on board.
Merchant crews at the time in the 2000s
were generally unarmed. And once even a
handful of armed pirates reached the
ship's bridge and seized control [music]
over the captain and officers, the ship
was usually theirs. The pirates would
then order the crew to sail their own
vessel back towards Somalia where it
could be anchored offshore beside one of
the piratec controlled coastal towns and
the long ransom negotiation process
could begin. It was around 2005 when the
introduction of mother ships completely
transformed the geographic scale of the
problem. Somali pirates were no longer
limited just to attacking ships passing
immediately beside their coastline.
After 2005, with mother ships, they
could remain out at sea for weeks at a
time and operate hundreds or even more
than a thousand kilometers away from
Somalia, covering a gigantic area
stretching from the Gulf of Aiden deep
into the western Indian Ocean. At the
same time, increasingly cheap and
available civilian technologies like GPS
receivers, satellite phones, weather
forecasts, and ship tracking information
made it far easier for relatively small
groups of pirates operating from fishing
boats to navigate across enormous
distances and coordinate attacks on some
of the largest commercial vessels on
Earth. These two separate graphs show
the number of reported piracy incidents
and hotspots from around the world on
the left and the number of reported
piracy hijackings in those same hotspots
around the world on the right. Between
about 2000 and 2006, the numbers of
piracy incidents and hijackings around
Somalia were not substantially different
than in other regions of the world like
West Africa and Indonesia. But after the
Somali pirates began using mother ships
around 2005 and after Somali warlords
began realizing just how much money
there was on the table and began
investing in a piracy. You can clearly
see the absolute explosion in Somali
piracy between about 2006 and 2011.
Somali pirates launched 111 attacks
against commercial ships in 2008.
another 218 attacks in 2009, 219 attacks
in 2010, [music]
and an all-time high of 237 attacks in
2011. By 2010 and 2011, at the peak of
the crisis, roughly half of all piracy
incidents in the world were taking place
in the waters around Somalia. And in
2010 alone, Somali pirates managed to
successfully hijack around 50 commercial
vessels. And there were as many as 700
sailors being held hostage in Somalia
simultaneously.
In 2011, when the number of attacks was
the highest, more than 1,200 sailors
were taken hostage by Somali pirates and
35 of them died while they were in
captivity. And some of the ships they
managed to capture during this period
were absolutely enormous. In November of
2008, [music] Somali pirates managed to
capture the Syria star, a Saudi super
tanker that was carrying roughly $100
million worth of the crude oil on board.
At more than 300 m long, the Sirius Star
was one of the largest ships ever seized
by pirates in history. [music] And its
capture demonstrated that virtually no
civilian ship in the region could simply
assume that it was too large or too
valuable to become a target. Then only a
few months after that, in April of 2009,
Somali pirates attacked the American
container ship Maris, Alabama, about 240
nautical miles off of the coast of
Somalia. An incident that became one of
the most famous pirate attacks of the
entire crisis. It was notably the first
time that pirates had managed [music] to
successfully capture a ship registered
under the US flag since the 19th
century, which brought the crisis into
the greater consciousness of the
American public. The crew managed to
regain control over their ship, but the
pirates escaped into a lifeboat with the
American captain, Richard Phillips, as
their hostage. The following standoff
lasted for several days until US Navy
Seal snipers aboard the USS Banebridge
managed to kill three of the pirates and
rescued Phillips alive. All of which was
later adapted into the blockbuster
Hollywood movie Captain Phillips a few
years later in 2013.
But most of the hijackings didn't end
with military rescues like that.
Usually, they ended months later with
huge piles of money. Once a captured
vessel was anchored off the Somalia's
coast, negotiators representing the
pirates and the ship owner could spend
months and sometimes even more than a
year arguing over the ransom price while
the crew remained trapped aboard. The
pirates had a powerful incentive to keep
all of their hostages alive because dead
sailors were ultimately worthless to
them. But that didn't mean that the
conditions of captivity were remotely
comfortable for the sailors. Hostages
could endure extreme heat, poor
sanitation, inadequate food and water,
disease, threats, beatings, and [music]
constant psychological pressure all
throughout their captivity, which on
average throughout the crisis lasted
somewhere between 4 and 8 months. While
some particularly unfortunate sailors
remained prisoners for more than 3
years. And over time, the ransoms being
demanded and earned by the pirates kept
getting bigger and bigger. In the
earlier years, around 2005, a ransom
might come in at below $200,000.
But by 2008, demands in the range of 1
to2 million had become more common. And
by 2010 and 2011, 3 to5 million ransoms
were becoming increasingly normal, with
exceptional cases even reaching beyond
$10 million.
In 2011, at the height of the crisis,
more than $150 million in ransoms were
collectively paid out to Somali pirates.
That year alone, big money was being
made. And once a final deal was agreed
upon, the ransom money would most often
be literally loaded up into waterproof
containers aboard a chartered aircraft
and then parachuted directly onto the
deck of the captured vessel where the
pirates would then count up the cash and
confirm its authenticity before finally
abandoning the ship and allowing the
crew to sail it safely away if
everything checked out. But despite
these massive ransom payments, the
pirates themselves were actually
capturing only a tiny fraction of the
total amount of money that their
activities were costing the global
economy. At the peak of the crisis
around 2010 and 2011, Somali pirates
were probably collecting somewhere
around 100 to $200 million per year in
ransom revenue. While the total
worldwide economic cost of Somali piracy
had soared to around 6 or7 billion
dollar annually, most of which was due
to dramatically higher insurance
premiums for ships operating in the
western Indian Ocean, security teams,
naval deployments, legal expenses,
shipping delays, additional fuel and
wages, and ships being forced to take
longer detours to avoid the most
dangerous waters. Eventually, the cost
became so high that much of the world
began treating Somali piracy almost like
it was a miniature war. Starting in the
late 2000s, an [music] extraordinary
coalition of countries began deploying
their warships into the waters around
Somalia to combat the piracy problem
that seems almost unthinkable today. The
US and its allies organized combined
task force [music]
151. The EU launched Operation Adalanta
in December of 2008, which is still
technically ongoing to this day, while
NATO established Operation Ocean Shield
in 2009. And beyond the traditional
Western alliances, countries as diverse
as Russia, China, India, Japan, and
South Korea all deployed their own naval
assets into the region as well. At the
peak, roughly 25 to 30 warships from all
around the world could be operating
around Somalia simultaneously,
representing one of the strangest
examples of international military
cooperation in the modern era, where
geopolitical rivals who disagreed about
almost everything else could at least
agree at the time that pirates hijacking
their merchant shipping was bad for all
of them. But the warships alone weren't
what defeated the pirates. The merchant
ships themselves [music]
also started making themselves
significantly harder to capture.
Shipping companies began adopting a wide
range of what became known as best
management [music]
practices or BMP for transiting through
pirateinfested waters. Crews installed
razor wire around vulnerable boarding
points. Used high pressure fire hoses
and water cannons to keep approaching
skiffs away. Traveled at higher speeds
whenever it was possible. Conducted
evasive maneuvers during attacks. and
constructed fortified panic rooms on
board their ships known as citadels
where the entire crew could retreat to
lock themselves inside, disable the
ship, and then wait for a nearby warship
to arrive. Surveillance aircraft,
satellites, and improved intelligence
sharing also made pirate mother ships
easier to identify and track before they
could launch their attacks. But probably
the single biggest development of all
was simply just putting armed security
guards on board the merchant ships.
>> [music]
>> Privately contracted security teams
carrying rifles began becoming
increasingly common aboard vessels
traveling through the region around
Somalia. And they presented the pirates
with a very simple problem. The pirates
entire business model basically depended
upon overwhelming unarmed civilian
sailors through intimidation alone. It
didn't work nearly as well when the
people on board the ship were actually
capable of shooting back. Publicly
reported data from the height of the
crisis indicates that not a single
merchant ship carrying an armed private
security team was ever successfully
hijacked after the practice became
widespread.
The economics of piracy therefore began
collapsing. Attacks were becoming
dramatically more likely to fail while
the chances of pirates getting killed,
arrested, or intercepted by a warship
were also increasing. The cost of
organizing pirate expeditions remained
high, but the likelihood of ever
collecting a ransom at the end was
falling. And since piracy had always
been primarily a business above anything
else, once it stopped being a
particularly good business to be
involved in, people just stopped
investing in it. The collapse in Somali
piracy happened with incredible speed.
After the all-time high record of 237
Somali piracy attacks in 2011, the
number collapsed to just 75 attacks the
next year in 2012 and then just 15
attacks in 2013 and only 11 in 2014. For
a whole decade between 2013 and late
2023, there was only one single
successful hijacking of a merchant
vessel that was made by Somali pirates,
which was an oil tanker called the Aerys
13 that was hijacked in March of 2017.
And it also ended in disaster for all of
the pirates involved after they found
out that the Aerys 13 had been hired by
a prominent Somali businessman and after
they subsequently found themselves in a
gunfight with local Somali authorities
over the ship's fate. They ended up
releasing the ship and its crew without
collecting any ransom just [music] 3
days after they had hijacked it. And
that was about it for Somali piracy for
roughly a decade. Somali piracy began
falling into the rear view mirror of
global issues as greater crises
elsewhere in Ukraine in the Middle East
began capturing [music] the headlines
instead. But the important thing to
understand about the decline of Somali
piracy across the 2010s and the early
2020s is that Somalia itself didn't
suddenly become a wealthy, peaceful, and
stable country. Many of the conditions
that had originally created piracy in
Somalia were still present. The country
remained deeply impoverished with little
economic opportunities. The federal
government still remained weak with
insurgent groups like Al-Shabaab still
controlling swaths of the country and
with secessionist and autonomydriven
factions effectively controlling their
own deacto independent states in both
the Somali land and hutland regions of
the country as well. Illegal fishing and
dumping both remain grievances in
coastal communities. Armed groups and
clan networks remained influential and
powerful. And many of the actual
pirates, financiers, negotiators, and
local networks that had participated in
piracy's golden age were never arrested
or dismantled [music] and had
effectively just gone dormant. They
simply stopped pirating because it had
become too difficult and too dangerous
to make enough reliable money from it.
Not because they were ever physically
eliminated. Many of them just returned
back to fishing again. Others moved on
to smuggling or joined with
insurgencies.
Some simply went home. But the knowledge
never disappeared. People still
remembered which communities could
support hijacked vessels, [music] how to
recruit crews, how to seize fishing
boats for use as mother ships, how to
identify vulnerable merchant vessels,
how to negotiate with foreign ship
owners, and how to distribute millions
of dollars of ransom money through local
clan and business networks. [music]
And beginning near the end of 2023,
after nearly a decade of dormcancy, some
of those networks started waking back up
again as geopolitical circumstances
shifted. In October of 2023, Hamas
launched a surprise attack on Israel
from the Gaza Strip, [music] triggering
Israel's subsequent invasion of Gaza and
the road to war all across the entire
Middle East. Weeks later, the Houthies
in Yemen began attacking merchant
shipping connected to Israel and the
United States in the Red Sea, which
triggered the formation of an
international naval coalition to
safeguard merchant travel through the
Red Sea against their attacks. The
spectre of Somali piracy was broadly
considered to be a thing of the past by
this point, and so many of the
international warships and naval assets
that have been dedicated to suppressing
them were transferred into action
against the Houthies instead. And with
that, some of the old dormant Somali
pirate networks began sensing a new
opportunity to strike again. In December
of 2023, just a couple of months after
the Houthies first began firing missiles
at commercial shipping in the Red Sea
and the world's navies reallocated their
resources to stop [music] them, Somali
pirates managed to capture the MD Ruin,
a Maltese flagged bulk cargo ship as it
was sailing off the coast of Somalia.
[music] It marked the first time that
Somali pirates had managed to
successfully hijack a merchant ship in
more than 6 years since the Aerys 13
back in 2017. And unlike the ARS 13,
they would hold on to it for a lot
longer than just 3 days. They took the
MB Ruin and its whole crew of 17 men
back to the Somali coast where they
spent time converting it into a mother
ship to go out and capture even more
ships. Three months later, in March of
2024, the pirates sailed the MB ruin
back out of sea again in this mother
ship role, hunting for more ships before
they were intercepted by two warships
from the Indian Navy. A 40-hour standoff
ensued before the pirates finally
surrendered the ship without collecting
a ransom. But the incident was clearly
something of an obit, showing that
Somali pirate networks were reactivating
again in light of the perceived
vulnerability of foreign warships
diverting away from Somalia to combat
the Houthies. And sure enough, many more
attacks would follow it. Across 2024,
eight attacks were recorded by Somali
pirates, the highest number in a single
year since [music] 2017. Most of them
were either unsuccessful or only
resulted in the capture of minor fishing
vessels. But one of them was an
undisputed triumph for the pirates. In
March of 2024, Somali pirates managed to
hijack the MV Abdullah, a Bangladesh
flag bulk carrier, as it was sailing
roughly 600 nautical miles off the coast
of Somalia, transporting 55,000 tons of
coal between Mosmbique and the United
Arab Emirates. The pirates then took the
ship and its entire crew back to the
Somali coast. and this time they were
actually able to collect on a ransom.
Reuters interviewed the pirates
afterward who claimed that they had
received a $5 million ransom payment
from the ship owner following 32 days of
negotiations.
This was extremely notable because it
was the first time in more than a decade
that Somali pirates managed to
successfully hijack a merchant ship and
collect a ransom. The last time that
this had happened was all the way back
in 2012 [music]
when Somali pirates had captured the MV
Smeirny and managed to collect a 9.5
million ransom for it 10 months later in
2013. [music] The few ships that Somali
pirates have captured since then were
always abandoned before they could
manage to collect on any ransom. And
then suddenly the successful capture and
$5 million ransom payment of the MV
Abdullah in 2024 proved not only that
Somali pirates could still capture a
major merchant ship. It also proved that
the old piracy business model of
hijacking a ship, anchoring it off
Somalia, negotiating, and then
collecting millions in ransom money was
still viable even after all this time
later. In a country that was still
politically shattered with few available
economic opportunities, just like it was
during the last time piracy had surged,
that was like a green light turning on
for the pirates to go out once again.
While 2025 was relatively quiet with no
successful merchant vessel hijackings by
the pirates, everything would begin
accelerating rapidly again in 2026.
>> [music]
>> Between the 21st of April and the 2nd of
May alone, multiple pirate armed groups
operating from Somalia carried out a
dense cluster of attacks and hijackings
of merchant vessels around the Somalian
Yemeni coasts, including the seizures of
the Honor 25, the Sword, and the Eureka
that we talked about at the start of
this video. [music] After the later
capture of the Asana in July, four
hijacked merchant vessels are currently
being anchored by the pirates off the
coast of Somalia with their entire crews
being held for ransom. The first time
that something to this scale has
happened since the peak of the Somali
piracy crisis back between 2010 and
2012. The current ransom being demanded
by the pirates for the release of the
Eureka alone reportedly escalated from
$3 million to $10 million. And as of
this video's writing, there is still no
resolution in sight. And there are
several reasons for why all of this is
beginning to happen again now. The
biggest factor is the power vacuum
that's currently taking place around
Somalia that is reexposing merchant
shipping to their attacks again. The
world's navies that once came together
to stop Somali piracy in the 2010s have
dramatically more problems competing for
their attention today in a global
environment that is significantly less
stable. NATO's European members are
primarily focused on defending against
Russia and the war raging across Ukraine
in the Black Sea today. The United
States committed naval assets to the Red
Sea to defend against Houthy attacks
there. And then at the end of February
this year, the US also launched a war
against Iran that resulted in the
closure of the straight of Hormuz and
the reallocation of even more US naval
assets to try and deal with it. I don't
believe that it's a coincidence at all
that only around 7 weeks after the US
launched its war against Iran, Somali
pirates began launching their own rapid
capture of merchant vessels again. The
EU has stated that its own Operation
Atlanta assets dedicated to combating
Somali piracy have not been reduced
because of the Middle East crisis, but
the broader international maritime
security environment is nonetheless
significantly more stretched than it was
back during the original antipiriracy
campaign of the 2010s.
Moreover, while Russia was a major
contributor to the naval coalition
against the Somali pirates back in the
early 2010s, right alongside NATO and
the EU, that cooperation is completely
unthinkable again today. NATO and the EU
were both effectively engaged in a cold
war with Russia over the Ukraine issue
and relations between them are extremely
hostile at the present. meaning that
cooperation and intelligence sharing
between them on a tertiary issue like
Somali piracy is just not going to
happen again today. And at the same
time, economic opportunity within
Somalia is still extremely poor. And if
anything, it's just been getting even
worse than usual. Recently, illegal and
unregulated foreign fishing in Somalia's
waters is still estimated to be costing
Somalia an average of $300 million a
year. and compounding the country's
economic woes even further. The Trump
administration has almost completely
eliminated all of the US developmental
programs to coastal Somali communities
that had been providing them with an
economic alternative to piracy for
decades. In 2024, during the final year
of the Biden administration, the US
provided Somalia with $476 million worth
of development aid, which the Trump
administration drastically reduced to
just $70 million in 2025. And during the
first three months of 2026, they only
sent $3 million to Somalia. At the same
time, rapidly rising food, fuel, and
fertilizer costs caused by the Iran war
and the shutdown of the Straight of
Hormuz have only further piled onto
Somalia's current economic misery. No
doubt pushing more men than usual to
consider resorting to piracy again. and
especially when they know that one group
of pirates managed to score a $5 million
ransom pretty recently in 2024. The
spike in oil prices has also meant that
Somali pirates are now incentivized to
target oil tankers because they know
that they can likely ransom them for a
higher profit. That's why it's also not
a coincidence that out of the four
merchant vessels that have been hijacked
by Somali pirates so far in 2026, three
of them have been oil tankers. The
rising shipping, insurance, and fuel
costs, all resulting from the Iran war
and the Houthies bombarding the Red Sea
also means that some shipping companies
are beginning to cut corners on their
security in order to save money,
reducing their numbers of armed security
that they place on board their ships,
which is exposing them more to piracy
attacks. And this time, the pirates
appear to be receiving more help from
the outside as well. On at least two
instances, at least according to US
intelligence, Somali pirates are
believed to have coordinated directly
with Houthi officials to plan their
attacks on commercial vessels. It
appears now that the Houthies have
agreed to help arm, train, [music] and
share intelligence with pirates from
Somalia in the hope of further
disrupting regional maritime commerce to
their own benefit, which was something
that was never happening back in the
2010s during the last Somali piracy
crisis. And Somalia itself is still a
very fragile country whose government is
still incapable of policing its own
waters. The federal government in
Somalia is vastly overstretched,
combating the al-Shabaab and ISIS
insurgencies that are still raging
across the interior of the country.
They're dealing with the secessionist
state of Somaliand that was recently
officially recognized as an independent
state by Israel. And they're also
dealing with local officials in the
Punkland region who have rejected the
federal government's authority and have
begun acting as another de facto
independent state within Somalia since
[music] 2024.
The Somali government still has
virtually zero bandwidth available to
stop pirates, especially with the almost
complete cut to all US development aid
and the recent rise in fuel, [music]
food, and fertilizer prices. For all of
these reasons, [music] it now seems
almost inevitable that the scourge of
Somali piracy, once thought to have been
solved for good back in the mid2010s, is
once again on the rise and rearing its
head in the western Indian Ocean. Now,
while you personally might not be
planning a sailing trip off the coast of
Somalia anytime soon, even your usage of
the internet right now in the safety of
your own home can still be pretty
dangerous. And a great way to add a
layer of security to whatever it is you
do on the internet is by using a trusted
VPN. Like this video sponsor, NordVPN.
With NordVPN's no logs policy, your
internet service provider isn't able to
see whatever it is that you're
searching. and neither does NordVPN,
which actually gives you a true
incognito viewing experience on the
internet that Google's incognito mode
doesn't truly provide. I especially like
to use Nord whenever I'm using
unfamiliar Wi-Fi networks at airports or
cafes. And Nord is much more than just a
VPN. I've known creator friends here on
YouTube who have gotten their accounts
hacked after a successful fishing
attempt or a password leak. and you've
maybe even seen one or two of them
yourself every so often whenever a
normal channel you love suddenly becomes
a crypto hype machine out of nowhere.
This unfortunately happens way too often
and NordVPN's threat protection include
specific features that warn you about
fishing links along with features like a
blocker for malicious ads and dark web
monitoring to alert you if any of your
passwords have been leaked. And of
course, NordVPN also does great VPN
things too. With Nord, you can safely
browse the internet anonymously, and
your location always stays private. It
enables me to set my location anywhere
in the world and access all of the
different versions of my favorite
websites. And it's the fastest working
VPN on the planet, too, that provides
247 customer support to help you
whenever you need it, along with a
30-day money back guarantee for all of
its users. So, if you'd like to give
NordVPN a try, scan the QR code here on
your screen or click the link down below
in the description. Every purchase of
the two-year plan will receive four
bonus months on top. And it's completely
risk-f free with Nord's 30-day money
back guarantee. So, click or scan to get
started with NordVPN today. It'll
greatly help out supporting my channel
at the same time. And as always, thank
you so much for watching.